A Guide to the Charles Vess Papers, 1978-2007, undated
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Charles Vess Papers 1978-2007, undated
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 374
.72 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The materials in this collection were donated to VCU Libaries by Charles Vess in the fall of 2007.
Biographical Information
Charles Vess is a respected fantasy art and comic-book illustrator whose work is within the realm of myths and fairy tales. He has won several awards, including Will Eisner Comics Industry Awards for his work on The Book of Ballads and Sagas, Neil Gaiman's Sandman, and Jeff Smith's Rose. In 1999, he was awarded the World Fantasy Award as Best Artist for his 175 paintings for Gaiman's novel Stardust.
Vess was born in Lynchburg, VA, and began drawing as a child. He went on to earn a BFA in Printmaking from Virginia Commonwealth University in 1974, and his first professional position was as a commercial animator for Candy Apple Productions in Richmond, VA. He later moved to New York City, did freelance for Heavy Metal Magazine, Klutz Press, and National Lampoon, and published The Horns of Elfland. In the 1980s, his career in fantasy comic art emerged with the publishing of Marvel Comics' The Raven Banner: A Tale of Asgard, "The Warriors Three Saga" in Marvel Fanfare, and Dark Horse Comics' Book of Night. In the 1990s, his notable mainstream work included the one-shot Spider-Man: Spirits of Earth and a 10-issue run as the cover artist for DC's The Swamp Thing. He also illustrated the official comic book adaptation of Steven Spielberg's Hook. During the early 1990s, Vess began self-publishing through his own Green Man Press studio.
As an illustrator, Vess is well-known for his collaborations and other commissioned work, most notably with Neil Gaiman (Books of Magic, Sandman, Stardust, and Blueberry Girl), Terry Windling and Ellen Datlow (The Green Man, The Faery Reel, and The Coyote Road), Charles de Lint (Seven Wild Sisters, A Circle of Cats, Moonheart, and Medicine Road), and George R.R. Martin (A Storm of Swords). VCU Libraries' Special Collections and Archives received these titles as a part of the donation from Charles Vess.
Scope and Content
The materials in these papers consist of Charles Vess' personal collection of his works including books with commissioned covers and illustrations. Many of these items are signed by Vess and the writers and are cataloged and housed in Special Collections and Archives. The 55 graphic novels and books have been added to the Stacks, and the 30 comic books featuring Vess' artwork were incorporated into the Comic Book Collection. Although the contents of the Charles Vess Papers primarily date from 1990-2007 with the exception being illustration plates from The Book of Night, dated 1978, the materials placed with the Comic Book Collection and the Stacks include his earlier works, particularly in the late 1970s and the 1980s, such as The Horns of Elfland (1979), The Harp and the Blade (1982), The Eggchild (1985), and Taboo #1 (1988).
Within the Charles Vess Papers, items that feature his artwork and other artists-notecards, postcards, and prints-are kept. In addition to the illustration plates from The Book of Night, the artwork series includes The Third Annual Tori Amos RAINN Benefit Calendar, which features various artistic renderings of the musician. Vess illustrated Amos as a faerie for the month of June. Several journals in which Vess and/or his work are featured were kept together. Unlike the comic books, graphic novels, and other books received, these journals are not housed with the other comic-art and fantasy related periodicals in order to maintain the original order and intent of Vess' papers. A few of the journals collected, such as Marquee and Sing Out, are not regularly kept by Special Collections and Archives, but these issues were saved by Vess because of his inclusion in those issues. Vess' papers also include a card from writer Theodora Goss, in which she thanked him for designing the cover of her chapbook The Rose in Twelve Petals and Other Stories.
Arrangement
Materials are organized into three series--Artwork, Correspondence, and Journals. Each series is in alphabetical order, then chronologically therein.
Contents List
- Artwork, 1978-2007, undated (Box 1)
  - Bone Art Print signed by Jeff Smith, 1999
  - Green Man Press Advertisements, 1997, 2003
  - Greeting Cards, 1992, 1997
  - Miscellaneous, 2007
  - Neil Gaiman and Charles Vess' Stardust Collectible Notecards, undated
  - Postcards, 1990, 1994, 2004, undated
  - Rose Art Print signed by Charles Vess, undated
  - Sandman postcard, 1996
  - Stardust postcards and invitations, 1998, 2007, undated
  - The Third Annual Tori Amos RAINN Benefit Calendar, 2006
  - "Visions from The Book of Night," 1978
- Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
  - Goss, Theodora, undated
- Journals, 1994-2007 (Box 1 and 2)
  - The Comics Journal, #218, 1999 December (Box-folder 1)
  - Faerie Magazine, 2006 Autumn (Box-folder 1)
  - Fantasy Worlds #5, 2005 February (Box-folder 1)
  - Feature #2, 1995 December/1996 January (Box-folder 1)
  - Highlander Magazine #34, 2001 July/August (Box-folder 1)
  - Indy Magazine #15, 1996 (Box-folder 2)
  - It Magazine & Comics #1, 1994 September (Box-folder 2)
  - Journal of the Fantastic in the Arts v.17 #2, 2006 Summer (Box-folder 2)
  - Locus v. 51 #1, 2003 July (Box-folder 2)
  - Marquee, 2004 Autumn (Box-folder 2)
  - Marquee, 2007 July/August (Box-folder 2)
  - Realms of Fantasy v. 13 #6, 2007 August (Box-folder 2)
  - Showcase Magazine, 2007 May (Box-folder 2)
  - Sing Out v. 40 #3, 1995 November-December/1996 January (Box-folder 2)
  - Sing Out v. 40 #4, 1996 Feb/March/April (Box-folder 2)
  - Sing Out v. 41 #1, 1996 May/June/July (Box-folder 2)
  - Sing Out v. 41 #4, 1997 Feb/March/April (Box-folder 2)
  - Starlog #358, 2007 August (Box-folder 2)